<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="en">
	<title>Unfathoming</title>
	<subtitle>I am writing about my experiences.</subtitle>
	<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/feed/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/"/>
	<updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
	<id>https://unfathom.ing/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Du Cheng</name>
		<email>youremailaddress@example.com</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The Bitcooiners were wrong</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/"/>
		<updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So too were the Ethereum...ers? Ethers? The people that shill Ethereum and Web3 as the solution to the world&#39;s problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-seven-principles&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The seven principles &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s seven fairly well known and agreed upon principles of Bitcoin. They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-custody: Bitcoin allows users to have full control over their own funds without relying on a third party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inclusion: Bitcoin is open and accessible to anyone with an internet connection, without discrimination or restrictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparency: The Bitcoin blockchain is a public, transparent ledger that records all transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy: Bitcoin transactions can be made with a high degree of privacy, without revealing users&#39; identities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decentralization: The Bitcoin network is decentralized and not controlled by any single entity, government, or organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No censorship: The Bitcoin network cannot prevent valid transactions from being confirmed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open-source: The Bitcoin software is open-source, allowing anyone to view and contribute to the codebase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every one of these seven principles are theoretically possible, but in reality near impossible to achieve. Lets break them down:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-custody&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Self-custody &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Not your keys, not your coins&amp;quot;. This is one of the biggest topics that bitcoiners talk about. It can be true depending on how you obtain and store your bitcoins. The problem I have with this is that the average person is using a custodial exchange, so while they think the bitcoins are stored in the app on their phone, they never even receive the seed phrase for them. This isn&#39;t necessarily a flaw with Bitcoin, but Bitcoin does nothing to prevent custodial exchanges, in the way something like Monero does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;inclusion&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Inclusion &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is inclusive for the most part, but its transparent design lacks plausible deniability, which means people in countries like China where Bitcoin is banned cannot safely use it in secret without hiding their trail. More on that in the next paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transparency&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Transparency &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a tragic success, and goes well with the next principle. The Bitcoin (and Ethereum) blockchain is too transparent. Anyone can see everything, meaning there is no privacy. If you were trying to hide your use of Bitcoin from your government, all it takes is one mistake to tie your entire transaction history back to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;privacy&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Privacy &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin offers no privacy. Absolutely none. The best you can do is use a non-KYC exchange or mine it yourself, then be very careful of who you send it to. Bitcoin is actually less private than your bank account, since the visibility into your bank account is regulated. Anyone with the time can dig through your Bitcoin (or Ethereum) transaction history, put the pieces together, and figure out who you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this to a bank account. Lets say you want to hide your donation to a political party from the world. With a bank account, you can just send the funds and in most cases, at least in the United States, they won&#39;t censor the transaction. With Bitcoin, you would have to use a mixer or similar tool to obfuscate the trace, which is yet another fee, and not actually private.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralization&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Decentralization &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of those things that is &amp;quot;in theory, but rarely in practice&amp;quot;. Most people use things like Coinbase, which are essentially PayPal for crypto. How Coinbase works, is if you send money to another user on Coinbase, no crypto is actually exchanged. The transaction is just stored on their centralized ledger (essentially just a database). For those who are using Bitcoin through non-KYC means, you&#39;re still going to interact with Coinbase and other centralized exchanges even if you aren&#39;t a user of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point that I&#39;d like to make on centralization, is that the vast majority of the Bitcoin network is operated by giant companies that run mining operations. It&#39;s become near impossible to actually mine bitcoin without hardware that costs thousands of dollars, leading to a few companies controlling all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-source&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Open-source &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one I can&#39;t really argue with. Bitcoin is open source, anyone can fork it and create their own blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;financial-privacy&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Financial privacy &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-bitcoiners-were-wrong/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of the problems that we see with Bitcoin, Ethereum, and derivatives are because there&#39;s no privacy. I wouldn&#39;t want to use a currency that anyone in the world can trace. China and North Korea are two countries that are known to track people overseas. Why should we give them one more tool to do so?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>My review of the private messaging ecosystem</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/"/>
		<updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commentary: I have considered lots of factors, including reviewing the latest data from the privacy spredsheet, but the content in this post is opinion, not fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been watching the state of private messaging for years, and have seen new companies enter with fresh ideas, which makes me excited to try out their products. I&#39;ve used just about every private messenger out there, and here&#39;s my review of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;element&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Element &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like Element, but their encryption has me wary of using it for anything sensitive because they&#39;ve had a few critical vulnerabilities in their rust crypto implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, it&#39;s a great discord-like platform, especially since you can self-host the whole thing and run your own community without having to follow any terms of service. They recently did a rewrite of their mobile apps and they look amazing. The web/desktop app is still a bloated JavaScript mess that feels disjointed. They could really use a native rewrite of the desktop app using something like QT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;signal&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Signal &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a longtime user of Signal, and I&#39;ve seen it get worse over the years with bugs, calls dropping, and messages never sending. With the update that brought usernames, they seemed to fix a lot of that, and it works well for my needs. The Mobilecoin rugpull was disappointing, especially considering they allow you to disable stories but not crypto features. They should&#39;ve gone with Monero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please Signal, if you&#39;re reading this, allow us to get rid of the crypto features like you did for stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simplex-chat&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;SimpleX Chat &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the one I&#39;m most hopeful for, due to its innovative lack of identifiers for users. I&#39;ve reviewed some of the code, as well as the designs, and while the app UI is quite ugly, the rest of it is excellent. It also has a 1GB per file upload limit, and it&#39;s quite fast to transfer files as well. I think this one will succeed, since it&#39;s also got mostly-functional large group support (it breaks around 600 members).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the fact that it doesn&#39;t rely on DNS for user identifiers, which boosts resiliency against censorship. This also removes the problem of bots picking up the best usernames and reselling them for 500x their listing price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;status&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Status &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I waited years for Status. I don&#39;t like how crypto is forced on users. Couldn&#39;t we have gotten a standalone messenger and been fine without the crypto integrations? It&#39;s not even Monero, it&#39;s a surveillance coin (ethereum). Their UI framework is top notch, but the way they executed on the mobile app is... questionable... and not the easiest to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Status touts &amp;quot;true ownership and self sovereignty&amp;quot; above all else. That&#39;s great, until you realize that you cannot export your account data for a backup which would be real ownership. The whole app also relies on the Waku network, which has limitations so severe that I can&#39;t use the app for anything useful. Seriously, 1MB per file, and only horribly compressed images allowed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metadata protection is great, until you use wireshark to analyze the app and you find out that it&#39;s connecting to about a dozen crypto providers, bittorrent.com (which is an advertiser nowadays), and a bunch of the company&#39;s own servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back on the topic of true ownership, if I can&#39;t self-host it on an airgapped network, I don&#39;t consider it true ownership. Showing off that I have some stupid .eth name or a picture of a poorly drawn monkey does not prove ownership, but being able to run the app myself on my LAN, as well as modify the code does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;telegram&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Telegram &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel gross calling this a private messenger, but it has optional, off-by-default, poorly implemented end-to-end encryption that only works on one-to-one chats, so I&#39;ll include it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since they introduced Telegram Premium, the app has become awful to use. Half of the features are paid, and many free features are now behind the paywall. It feels desperate and it&#39;s sad to see a decent (but bloated) messenger with useful features become an advertisement for their premium stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&#39;ve also gotten in on the crypto hype with TON coin, their crypto which (like most crypto projects) is a solution in search of a problem. You can buy usernames with it and that&#39;s about it. Just more bloat in an already bloated messenger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whatsapp&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;WhatsApp &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/my-review-of-the-private-messaging-ecosystem/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the one I&#39;ve used least out of them all. They recently overhauled it with AI integrations in places that are quite odd and very inappropriate for a messenger that advertises itself as private, but what can you expect from Facebook?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Why I use Linux</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/"/>
		<updated>2024-03-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lots of people ask me why I use Linux, so I thought I&#39;d put it here. TLDR; I use Linux because its the only option that respects the user and doesn&#39;t spy on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve used Windows in recent years, you&#39;ve probably noticed a sharp decline in usability, an increase in ads, and a general enshittification of the platform. I&#39;ll break down all of the things that anger me with other operating systems. Prepare for a rant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;control&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Control &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I use Windows and (especially) MacOS, I feel like I don&#39;t have much control over the system. I want to do updates if and when I want. I do not want the Microsoft Corporation telling me its time to update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to controlling if and when I update, I also want to control what background processes are happening on my system. I do not want Teams, Edge, Bing, or anything else running around on my system without my consent. I want to be able to uninstall any software I want, even if it has the possibility of breaking my system. Windows and MacOS come with lots of bloatware, and there&#39;s no easy way to remove it, thus, you do not truly own your computer when you run Windows or MacOS on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;privacy&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Privacy &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t want Microsoft or Apple virtually looking over my shoulder or scanning my files. I deal with a lot of sensitive information, and the files on my machines need to be under my control. I do not want Microsoft enabling OneDrive and uploading all of my data to their cloud after one of the many mandatory updates. Privacy is one of my core values, and is something that both Windows and MacOS violate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the moment you set up a Windows machine, you&#39;re begged for a Microsoft account, and you either need to use registry hacks or change your location to the United Kingdom to bypass the mandatory Microsoft account page. Most users sigh and create an account or sign in with an existing one, without realizing that this ties all of what you do to that account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these problems are eliminated with Linux. None of the popular distributions require online accounts, and the majority don&#39;t even ask for them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;security&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Security &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, Windows is a security shitshow. Downloading EXEs from the internet should&#39;ve been deprecated long ago in favor of a package manager, yet here were are in 2024 with malicious downloads still being a huge problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also not a big problem on #linux. Sure, malware exists, but if you stick to verified repositories and don&#39;t download random .deb files from the first search result you see, you&#39;ll be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;drivers&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Drivers &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunting down and installing drivers feels like something that should&#39;ve been solved for in the year 2000, yet I did that just last week for someone. Shipping drivers with the kernel causes less issues, improves security, and makes installing the distro a far more seamless experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;politics&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Politics &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just want my computer to do the basics without getting political. I don&#39;t care about pride month, black history month, or anything else that Windows loves to shove into the search box or other UI elements. None of it interests me, I just want a computer that does computing, not American politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux distro developers don&#39;t try to force American politics on users. Keep up the great work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;respects-default-settings&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Respects default settings &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/why-linux/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve used Windows 11, you probably have had the experience of having to change your default browser back to Chrome or Firefox from Edge every few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox is usually the default, and while I don&#39;t use non-chromium browsers (besides Tor), I appreciate that it&#39;s not forced and I can change it to whatever I want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI (or lack thereof)
AI can be great (when its not politically biased), but I don&#39;t want it in my OS or apps. Both Windows and MacOS fall into the &amp;quot;shiny hype train&amp;quot; trap by including AI. If I want AI, then I will visit the ChatGPT website or install an offline AI program for more privacy, but don&#39;t force it on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly there are some Linux distros that have hopped on the AI hype train, but thankfully none of the more popular ones have.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The tragedy of Discord</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/"/>
		<updated>2024-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve seen more and more communities utilizing Discord (the social chat app) as a means of organization and communication. It’s not just the big names either, it seems to be every community that isn’t privacy focused, as well as most “Web3” communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: To help migrate users away from IRC, Discord chose to name their communities “servers”. Servers in this context are nothing more than folders where text files (which they call channels) are stored. It is impossible to host a Discord server on your own hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;discord-is-bad-for-the-open-web&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Discord is bad for the open web &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably heard someone complain about the LinkedIn authentication popups that require you to sign in to view content. The frustration you feel when you go to check on someones profile, only to be hit with a “sign up to LinkedIn” prompt is the same frustration I and others feel towards communities on Discord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the answer to your problem existing on a forum that’s indexed by the major search engines, you spend hours digging around just to realize that the solution is buried deep inside of a community on Discord, and the only way to view it is to let them collect your data so you can join what should’ve been a public forum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;centralization&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Centralization &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We put a huge emphasis on privacy and do not track the user or attempt to associate their queries with any identifiers like an IP or cookie. Both our clearnet and Tor mirrors run all logic on the backend, meaning no JavaScript or WASM on the frontend. The entire search engine has been designed with the idea that someday we may get a subpoena, and we want to confidently tell the lawyers that we collect only the absolute minimum required to operate and we don’t even store it on disk (memory-only).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see no reason for Google, Bing, or others to store every search you make over the entire history of your account, unless they’re selling it to the CIA or something. Spooky!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;absolutely-proprietary&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Absolutely proprietary &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the claims by the company that “Discord loves open-source” they in fact do not. Nothing about Discord is open source beyond some of the GPL licensed projects that they rely on for their own code. This doesn’t sound like a company that loves open source and wants to contribute back. This sounds like a company that loves open source because it makes their own development cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those that have attempted to reverse engineer and re-implement the Discord technology stack in an open-source way have been hit with legal notices. Just look at what they did to Fosscord and other projects that are re-implementations of their specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;server-operators-are-powerless&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Server operators are powerless &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a server operator, you are powerless against the platform. You have no say in what features they decide to add or remove, and what other things they do. There have been instances where Discord have purposely made the platform worse for some users as an April Fools joke. Is that the kind of platform you want to rely on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moderators-have-no-say&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Moderators have no say &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the company introduces new features, they are typically Nitro (their 10 dollar monthly subscription) exclusive, or severely limited unless you pay. To access some of these features, your community must be paying for Nitro in order to get “Boosts” which can be used to make your server significantly more useful to everyone. The main problem? This collectively costs 140 dollars per month for the highest tier, and it is on a per-server basis. Every server that wants a decent experience must expect their members to collectively cough up $140 a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moderators-have-no-power&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Moderators have no power &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike hosting your own community forum or Matrix server, you cannot ban a block of IPs that are used by adversaries to evade bans on Discord. Why? You do not own your server, the company does. The only one with power over your community is Discord themselves. This is a problem for server operators since Discord has very weak alt detection and ban evasion is trivial, as the checks happen client side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord lulls you into a false sense of ownership and control, when in reality you own nothing beyond the branding of the server and the messages you send. Put bluntly, if Discord decides you don&#39;t make them enough money, or you mention alternative platforms, they can delete a community you&#39;ve built over years and you can do nothing about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moderators-have-no-privacy&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Moderators have no privacy &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither do their communities. For the communities that are intentionally private (meaning they have no public invite links), they also have no privacy. All it takes is one data breach or a misconfiguring of permissions, and your entire chat history including deleted messages is open to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-users-are-powerless-as-well&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;End users are powerless as well &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an end user, you have no power or control over the platform. Just like server operators, you have no say in what features the company chooses to add or remove, and without using a custom client, you have no way to fix the intentionally bad design unless you pay for the Nitro monthly or yearly subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;users-have-no-say&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Users have no say &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a user of Discord, you have absolutely zero say in how the platform is run. In fact, the platform is designed to push users towards its Nitro subscription by restricting users who don’t pay, and imposing artificial limitations upon them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of this is themes. Users have been using tools like BetterDiscord to customize the look and feel of the platform. Some users do this for accessibility, although most do it because the default experience is just plain awful. What does Discord do in this case? They add themes for 10 dollars a month and start banning users who openly talk about their use of client modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;users-have-no-power&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Users have no power &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have no power or control over Discord, your data, or your account. You can’t even have the option to sue them unless you let them know and tell them your legal name and other personal information within a month of creating your account, regardless of if you actually plan to sue them, which is not something you should want to give a company that works with the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;users-have-no-privacy&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Users have no privacy &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have no control or insight into how Discord uses your data. This should scare you, especially considering their investment and data sharing agreements with Tencent; a company with an awful track record regarding privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your DMs on Discord are not end-to-end encrypted, which means employ ees can read your messages. Their “trust and safety” employees are untrustworthy, and have been known to read the direct messages of their friends, as well as ban users entire accounts as a joke. Privacy and anonymity do not exist on Discord at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-platform-is-a-disaster&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The platform is a disaster &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord compels users to follow their Terms Of Service by threatening to delete their accounts, but then never does anything about the outsiders who abuse the platform. This leads to a situation where consequences only apply to legitimate users who want to keep their accounts. Bots, spammers, and loggers can do whatever they want.
Funny how that works, isn&#39;t it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-makes-this-a-tragedy&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;What makes this a tragedy? &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/2024/the-tragedy-of-discord/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have willingly given up the freedoms and privacy that they had on IRC and Matrix to move towards a centralized platform that is hostile towards them, does not care about them, and actively exploits them for monetary benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of decentralized communities that are truly owned by their leaders / moderators, millions of people moved away from IRC and other decentralized offerings towards the flashy marketing and gamer aesthetic™. People have willingly given up freedoms and privacy for convenience and in the process they’ve also lost what made the early internet communities special; their sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord does not care about you, despite the flashy marketing. Discord does not care about people with disabilities, despite their modern UI. Your privacy is an obstacle to their success. If you’re thinking about starting a Discord server, please consider an alternative such as self hosting Element, or if you must have the Discord UI and don&#39;t mind a strong liberal bias, Revolt is an open-source option that might work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my fourth post!</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/fourthpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/fourthpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/img/IdthKOzqFA-350.avif 350w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/img/IdthKOzqFA-350.webp 350w&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A possum parent and two possum kids hanging from the iconic red balloon&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/img/IdthKOzqFA-350.png&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; height=&quot;685&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/fourthpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my third post.</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-08-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;code&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Code &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;styled-with-syntax&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Styled (with Syntax) &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// this is a command&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;myCommand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; counter &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	counter&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Test with a line break above this line.&lt;/span&gt;
console&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;Test&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;unstyled&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Unstyled &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// this is a command
function myCommand() {
	let counter = 0;
	counter++;
}

// Test with a line break above this line.
console.log(&#39;Test&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my second post with a much longer title.</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/secondpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-07-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/secondpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/secondpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/firstpost/&quot;&gt;First post&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/thirdpost/&quot;&gt;Third post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my first post.</title>
		<link href="https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/firstpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-05-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/firstpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://unfathom.ing/unfathoming/blog/firstpost/&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-diff-js&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-diff-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token unchanged language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix unchanged&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// this is a command&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix unchanged&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;myCommand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token inserted-sign inserted language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix inserted&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; counter &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token deleted-sign deleted language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix deleted&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; counter &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token unchanged language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix unchanged&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;  counter&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix unchanged&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token unchanged language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix unchanged&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Test with a line break above this line.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix unchanged&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;console&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&#39;Test&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
